A Guide to the Joe Jackson Papers, 1984-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Joe Jackson Papers, 1984-1999
The Library of Virginia
43778
3.375 cubic feet (8 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joe Jackson, Virginia Beach.
Biographical Information
Joe Jackson is the author of one novel and six nonfiction titles. From 1997 to the present, he has been a full-time author and journalist. Jackson holds an MFA from the University of Arkansas and was an investigative reporter for the Virginian-Pilot newspaper in Norfolk for twelve years, covering criminal justice and the state's Death Row. He was the writer-in-residence at the James Thurber House in 2001. His foreign assignments included Russia and the Baltic republics, where he covered the bloody 1991 revolution in Lithuania. Jackson currently lives in Virginia Beach with his wife, Kathy.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1984-1999, of Joe Jackson (b. 1955) of Virginia Beach, relating to his research and co-authorship of Dead Run: The Untold Story of Dennis Stockton and America's Only Mass Escape from Death Row, published in 1999. The book details the case of death row inmate Dennis Stockton (1940-1995), as well as the escape of six fellow inmates at the Mecklenburg Correctional Center on 31 May 1984. The collection includes clippings, correspondence, drafts, galleys and a copy of the book, notes, and legal documents, including affidavits, appeals, motions, orders, petitions, and trial transcripts that were filed in the Patrick County (Va.) Circuit Court, Virginia Supreme Court, United States District Court for the Western District of Virginia, United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, and the United States Supreme Court.
The collection also contains numerous writings of Dennis Stockton while he was a prisoner on death row at the Powhatan Correctional Center and the Mecklenburg Correctional Center. They include both fiction and non-fiction works, entitled "The Daybook" (1990), "Joshua" (1992), "Passin' Thoughts" (1993), "Bits 'n' Pieces" (1994), "Humdingers" (1994), "This 'n' That" (1994), and "The Last Chapter (1995). In addition, there are letters from Stockton to William F. Burke, Jr., a reporter with the Virginian-Pilot newspaper and Jackson's co-author on Dead Run, concerning the publication of a diary Stockton kept while he was incarcerated. The diary excerpts were published by the newspaper as "Death Row Diary" on 16 September 1984, and later diary excerpts were published in 1995. Also among Stockton's writings in the collection are diary entries from August to September 1984, and a prison newsletter he authored, also entitled "Passin' Thoughts," covering the years 1992 to 1995.
Contents List
- Anti-Death Penalty Literature. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Bits 'n' Pieces". (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
- Briley, Linwood and James. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brown Bag Lunch on Clemency, 15 January 1997. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Clippings. (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
- Coleman, Roger Keith. (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Coppola, Frank. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence - Dennis Stockton to William F. Burke, Jr. 1984 (June-December). (Box 2, Folder 4-7)
- Correspondence - Dennis Stockton to William F. Burke, Jr. 1993-1995. (Box 2, Folder 8-10)
- Correspondence - Other Inmates. (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence - Publishing, Permissions, Copyright. (Box 2, Folder 12-14)
- "The Daybook". (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
- Dead Run: The Untold Story of Dennis Stockton and America's Only Mass Escape from Death Row - Book. (Box 3)
- Dead Run: The Untold Story of Dennis Stockton and America's Only Mass Escape from Death Row - Galleys. (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
- Death Row and Religion. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "Death Row Diary," Virginian-Pilot/Ledger Star, 16 September 1984. (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Diary, August-November 1984. (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
- Diseases - Histoplasmosis. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "Drugs: Understanding the War," 6-11 May 1990. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- "Echo from the Inside" - Prison Newsletter, 1993. (Box 4, Folder 7)
- "Escape from Death Row" - Outline. (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Evans, Wilbert Lee. (Box 4, Folder 9)
- "Every Means of Escape: A Life on Death Row" by Joe Jackson and William F. Burke. (Box 4, Folder 10-14)
- "Humdingers". (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- "Joshua". (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
- "The Last Chapter". (Box 5, Folder 6-11)
- Last Statement, 27 September 1995. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- "A Life on Death Row" - Outline, Synopsis, etc.. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- "A Life on Death Row" by Joe Jackson and William F. Burke - Rough Draft. (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
- News Accounts of 1984 Prison Escape and Manhunt. (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Norfolk Capital Murders. (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Notes. (Box 6, Folder 7-10)
- Notes on Execution. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Notes - Newspaper Stories - ATEX Files. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- "Passin' Thoughts". (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
- "Passin' Thoughts" - Prison Newsletter. (Box 7, Folder 1)
- "Reflections on the Guillotene". (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Roach, Steve - Drawings. (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Stockton, Dennis - Legal Documents. (Box 7, Folder 4-11)
- Stockton, Dennis - Other Writings. (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Stockton, Dennis - Other Writings - Used. (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Stockton, Dennis - Powhatan and Mecklenburg Writings, 1994-1995. (Box 7, Folder 14)
- "This 'n' That". (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
- Turner, Willie Lloyd. (Box 8, Folder 5)
- United Nations Commission on Human Rights. (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Will of Dennis Walden Stockton. (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Wise, Joe and Roach, Steve. (Box 8, Folder 8)